this is software engineering radio the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at se - radio dotnet
I see radio brings you relevant detailed
discussions about software engineering
topics at least once a month
thanks to our audience and the partners
listed on our website for supporting the
podcast
[Music]
hello welcome to ass your radio this is
an episode that is a little bit
different that some of the others we've
done before because it's a little bit
kind of a little bit off topic but it's
still close to what we were talking
about usually which is obviously
computer and software this one is more
about hardware it's specifically about
chip production chip manufacturing with
a focus on the wafers scanners that are
used to project the structures of the
chip onto the wafer I recently had the
chance to well not so recently I had the
chance to talk to people at ASML they
manufactured these wafers scanners in
Eindhoven and in the Netherlands and
this is the result of this conversation
it's an interview with Wilbert Albers
who is a software engineer at this
company this episode has been previously
published in Omega tau my other podcast
on science topics so if you've listened
to that you probably want to skip this
episode it's the same content but as I
know from the statistics most people who
listen to su radio don't listen to Omega
tau so we thought we'd we'd kind of
cross publish it here because it really
affects both communities so well if you
like this kind of stuff you probably
want to subscribe to make out how in the
future but we thought we'd bring you
this one on the AC radio channel as well
so as I like to say oh my god how as
usual we start with our guest
introducing himself so you know who he
is
well I'm also I'm a software engineer at
a is Mel and I am ready quite some time
at age Mel I started here in 1998 just
as a coding guy for a subsystem we call
radical stage then I got into
architecture I got involved into the
software architecture of a
synchronization control component
because synchronizing various subsystems
is a very important aspect you know
wafer scanner and later on I also got
involved into the architecture of an
specific wavefront aberration sounds oh
okay we'll have to talk about that later
I guess but in general it was in the
last 10 years a lot of architecture and
then from getting very specific to more
and more
generic enough yeah that's it I'm being
so ASML by the way do the letters ASML
stand for anything if I'm writing are
for advanced semiconductor manufacturing
lithography okay good
which introduces the topic we're going
to talk about chip production and
specifically wafers scanners which are
the lithography machines that put you
know the chip layout well we talked
about that onto the chip so I guess
before we talk about chip production
maybe a quick overview of about what a
wafer scanner does so like and what your
company does in the space in order to
make chips you need to be able to
project a very detailed image on a very
small surface and that projection is
done with a device called a wafer
scanner so we have a light source we
have a mask then there the pattern that
needs to be projected we have a piece of
optics and lens and then we have a
substrate which is the wafer which will
be receiving the pattern obviously in
order to make some sense this wafer has
to be coated with some photoresist yeah
in front talk about that later of course
so in some sense the the wafer scanners
are if you will the core of chip
production because a lot of the other
stuff is mechanical / chemical and this
is you know this puts the chips
structures onto the silicon definitely
and what makes it a different kind of
equipment with regard to the rest is
that a lot of the other process I think
all other processes are done on a way
from as a whole and our scanner is doing
them chip by chip which emphasizes the
requirements that we have with respect
to through boot right because if the
rest gets a little bit faster we have to
get a lot faster who died yeah okay so
we'll get back to that later ASML is
some vendor of these machines maybe you
don't talk a little bit about the
company so people know who we were
talking to kind of yeah we are they
smell our company of all of 7,000 people
situated in the veldt although most of
our customers are in asia so we have a
larger support organization in Asia and
also a department in in America we
designed the systems definitely
ourselves the optics in close
cooperation with Zeiss in Germany
although manufacturing of the thing is
for larger part outsourced to a lot of
companies especially obviously here in
the region of Eindhoven we put the thing
together here at the Veldhoven and
customers come do some testing and agree
to buy the failure then we take it down
again and to ship it to our customers as
I had shipped and in parts and she
definitely shipped impossible ok so
let's talk about the general process of
trip production first and then we're
going to you know delve deeper in the in
the way of a scanner aspect of it I
guess to set the stage chips are what
powers computers phones and as
understood increasingly memory is also a
big big market so maybe we can talk a
little bit about what what is you know
how his chip looks what what is the chip
so we know what we are building in this
episode well I know that when I broke up
my my first the television set I know
there were a lot of discrete components
in it and when I opened one later
revision there was there was printed
circuit boards and they called contain
those black box and well that was where
it stopped because we had a lot of pins
in it and there was going on a lot of
magic in it and well you could not make
any sense out of it anymore so those are
the chips and where it starts with is
really a big layer of a big disk of
silicon yeah we call that a wafer and a
wafer is going to hold a lot of those
yeah so how big are chips if you look at
the I don't know Pentium CPU or whatever
they're called these days well you
should look to your little pinky and
look at the nail of your little pinky
that's the size of a typical chip okay
and how many transistors roughly I mean
the transistors are the the core
building blocks right the the
interconnection of those make up the
function of the chip and there are
billions of transistors on a chip really
they are incredibly small
any numbers I mean how small are I don't
know the connections how thin are the
connectors the connecting in our systems
we are faced with requirements like
overlay and critical dimension and the
critical dimension is the smallest
structure we illuminate this is
inaudible tens of nanometers so it's 10
to the power of minus 9 minus 10 so um
before we again before we look at the
production that the transistors are the
basic building blocks and I assume that
some people listening to this episode
know what a transistor is others
probably don't I should know it because
I'm a I studied physics at some point
but I'm not sure I'm still really sure
about it so what is the transistor well
in fact it's just a switch so that means
that we have three important points on
this transistor you need to have two
points that need to be connected or need
to be disconnected depending on the
state of the switch and you need to have
a lever which enables you to switch so
those 3 connection points in the most
technology are called the source the
drain and the gate gate is the one that
switches definitely yeah that's the
lever so these points need to be
identified in a transistor and you know
we make a lot of them and they're very
bottom layer of the silicon disk on this
wafer and yeah the way they are
connected determines the function of the
chip and how does it work on a physical
level I mean how is this switching yeah
what's done there well this is done is
that the silicon substrate a search does
not conduct so it's resistant and by
contaminating it with certain materials
which are having an electron in surplus
or lacking just one electron you can
make this silicon substrate
semiconducting and then by applying a
current you get a field into the
substrate which makes the whole area
between the source and the drain
conducting or not which enables you to
switch so in other words that the
purpose of producing these transistors
that are part of a chip is to first of
all inject these contaminations yeah
that's where we start with right and
then two identical
the microscopic structures which
identify these three points so you can
connect other stuff to and then putting
all the connection connecting lines on
to the tip
only the lowest layer and because chips
are built in layers right only the
lowest layers hold the transistors and
the rest of it only connects them in
certain ways yeah obviously you cannot
make all connections in one way because
then you would have a lot of contacts
that you wouldn't want to these layers
are like bridges and tunnels yeah yeah
there are some on the internet you can
find some some pictures yeah off such a
chip you can really see those 3d
stretches okay I guess we'll put some of
these pictures into the show notes as
links so is it fair to say that the
intellectual property well I should say
differently the functionality of the
chip is not in the transistors it's a
it's in the connections between the
transistors yeah that's true
so the problem so if you might build
different transistors for different
application purposes then maybe the
transistor structure is always the same
it's always transistors organized maybe
in a grid or something and then the
trick is in the connections it is done
like that although for different
purposes different kind of transistors
can be made okay being either very
efficient with regard to power
consumption okay very fast yeah okay
make sense but but the hole okay then
the trick is in the interconnections
yeah definitely okay good and and we
already talked about the fact that there
how many layers are there typically it's
about your of 20 or 30 layers okay yeah
yeah and I guess that's where this this
precision comes from because if if the
layer 18 doesn't connect to the right
pin that comes from one of these points
in one of the transistors then you're
lost yeah you make a short-circuit and
you get a lot of frustration when you
have such a chip in your computer
because yeah well hopefully it doesn't
work at all but maybe sometimes it works
a little bit yeah yes yeah so and it's
used for maybe that's also something I
didn't know before that the growth for
you and your customers today is not so
much in processors but also in memory oh
yeah we a lot of our customers are
memory customers affect their roadmap is
a little bit more aggressive than the
the logic as we call them
the logic is a real intelligent thing
like the Intel and AMD snare micro
processors are doing
memories more regular we can shrink more
efficiently we can tune the process more
efficiently towards memory and Megaman
that way and a more aggressive and
faster progressing in technology okay
just to clarify what we are going to
talk about in this episode we are not
going to talk about chip design like how
do you do the connections in order to
build an Intel Itanium processor and to
have all these fancy things with branch
prediction and stuff that's not what
we're talking about we're talking about
the morals physical production of the
processor after it has been designed yes
I think that's a good separation because
today what we have in the industry is
that chip manufacturing is often
separated from I think they're called
foundries who actually built the program
the chip yeah I know of companies like
Leena Stovall said yeah that's me do
something like there and also you really
got into outsourcing their production to
a company that made the physical chilly
out of them
yeah yeah I heard that that's also right
relatively typical in the in the
industry yeah so let's talk about chip
production and I guess again this can be
separated into at least two stages one
deals with the wafer and one deals with
the chip
so maybe you should define what a wafer
is first yeah well the wafer is the disc
of silicon a little bit more than one
millimeter thick and well they have been
common various sizes and there used to
be even smaller than 200 millimeters but
200 millimeters was a typical size and
with a diameter of the diameter yes
exactly and now we are working with
mostly with 300 millimeter wafers and
the reason about forgetting better and
waifus size is that a lot of steps
during the production are done on a
wafer basis and then it doesn't make
sense whether you are just coating or
possessing one one millimeter disc all
three and handling is the same you get
more out of it but you get definitely
more out of the lot more so where does
the wafer come from I mean I know that
silicon is basically sand yeah
the male descent and then they grow out
a crystal out of it
one big regular crystal it gets a real
cone of silicon and then they make
slices of it
okay and switches right they cut it down
and then slices a waiver why is it
important that it's grown how does it
have to be very regular if it wouldn't
be a mono crystal the yield of the
successful chips that can be made of it
decreases due to the imperfections of
that crystal okay and then transistors
don't just switch propyl anymore okay I
see so okay so the quality of the of the
silicon wafer is important for the
functioning of the chair later okay so
we have the big cone of silicon we cut
it down and I guess it's a challenge to
not destroy the whole surface when you
cut it yeah well I don't know how they
do here even that is a big challenge
yeah but let's face it in the end you
have to cut it down in smaller pieces
and then you have to cut it down without
destroying the rest of the chips how do
you do that yeah well they I've seen one
one movie out of that a heavy so always
a circular motion going over this way
from and well obviously you have to be
very well with the position of that saw
in order to go just between the chips
and the other have put there they put it
in water I think just to make it very
smooth so that's not part of a waiver
scanner no that's not not but it's also
the wafer has been spared a lot of time
yeah okay so um we now have the wafers
yeah and next step is well the
transistor should go in the bottom layer
and that means that the silicon is we
couldn't use the introduction its
insulating so we have to contaminate it
at very specific spots spots that Omega
T transistor connection points later on
so what we do with it is that we start
to coat the whole wafer when they drop a
photoresist and then we spend away from
so we the whole wafer gets coated with a
nice layer of photoresist photoresist is
one chemical fluid which is
reacting on illumination of a life is a
certain wavelength so so when you when
you when you light the photo resistant
what what happens well the the
properties of the illuminated areas
change in such way that we can develop
the photo just like an old photograph
and then we can etch away the areas that
have been illuminated all the areas that
have not been illuminated okay so and
then what we end up with is away from
where certain parts are covered still
with photoresist and all the parts the
photoresist has been etched away so we
are looking on the Bay of silicon again
and when we have such a way for where
those holes are punched into it with the
photoresist we can contaminate that area
precisely with these materials that have
the contaminating nature so the whole
point of this photoresist is to
basically put a mask on to the silicon
with holes in it yeah and these holes
are then used to as the places where the
silicon is contaminated exactly yeah
okay so the purpose of the wafer
scanners is making the illumination
illuminating the photoresist with the
pattern okay showing the holes
especially in the first layer of metal
layers different patterns are used
because then we are not making the holes
but connections yeah well then these the
patterns are then lines and dots but
yeah but your your machines that the
wafer scanners are used in all these
layers oh yeah okay so okay so we're
going to talk about the way for scanners
later in detail but so once we have the
lowest layer with the transistors and
once we've done the etching so we have
done the contamination mhm I mean how do
you put additional layers on top of it
you have to insulate an insulator will
be common between and also then that
insulating layer will be coated with
photoresist again we're going to etch
away those areas that we need to bring
on top again and then we are going to
coat it not with the resistant layer but
with a conductive layer like aluminum or
copper and then we're going to etch the
top surface
but where the holes were those holes get
filled with a little stack of aluminum
and so that gives you the vertical
corner here's my vertical connection
exactly okay okay well then you can
imagine that this process gets repeated
each time after a euro right and you can
also imagine that it is very important
to be right on spot there the next layer
yeah yeah otherwise the vertical
connections obviously don't touch
anything sensible yeah out there yeah
okay
so during chip production is there a way
how you can do any kind of you know
quality control I mean if you're
building 18 layers do you know that the
seventh of them has been correctly built
or can you only do a black box test of
the whole chip once it's finished I do
not know where where we go a cable of
testing the function of the chip at an
early stage but I do know that we are
capable of measuring the quality of
certain illuminated structures so you
can say you you have some ways to do
some intermediate measurements but I
don't know whether they are done on a
regular scale if you are in control of
your process that you just continue
going on and then in the end do the
black box measurements they don't work
well it's correct by construction versus
testing right I mean if you're sure that
your machines are you know correctly
positioned and everything is great
because you've verified that somehow
before then you don't have to do testing
and obviously a lot of testing and then
measuring and then tuning of those
processes all like how much photoresist
is needed there how long should it be
illuminated how long should the etching
be done yeah well that is obviously done
upfront on a smaller scale yeah right I
guess you spend years optimizing these
machines before they're kind of sold to
customers I don't know because well it
has it is very important for Christmas
to be first in the market before they're
competitors so there there's always a
time pressure and I think yeah this
whole production stuff when is also
happening in a clean room clean room
environment right yeah also the whole
machine building I guess has to happen
in a building Europe is cameras has to
happen at cleanroom right yeah
we have a clean room they think the
clean room environment a very very clean
environment because any particles that
are flying around over there when they
enter our machine they might end up and
a way for which gives you a
malfunctioning ship but it might even be
worse when they end up on the mass
calling the pattern because a particle
that ends up on the mask will be
projected in every chip on the wafer so
then you have no good it's very
interesting environment if people are
all wearing the same dress and sometimes
especially in for the next generation
systems they are wearing a mouth caps so
I know that I've seen people and worked
with them a day and it might not
recognize you one day in the restaurant
not wearing the suit okay so let's look
at the well and then of course there is
one more step in the production that is
obviously cutting as we talked about
before cutting the finished chips down
in well cutting the wafers down into
separate chips yeah and then they need
to be put into those little black houses
yeah and then they have today their
depends of the outside of those houses
have to be connected with called bonding
bonded with the inside connection points
on the silicon die
how many connectors does a chip have
today typically it's in the hundreds
it's honest yeah when you turn upside
down a Pentium chip on AMD chip you see
a lot of connection point right yeah
when I wasn't when I was a kid as they
say I played around with these ICS as we
called them then like 10 or 20 G's and
connectors below were only at the sides
now with modern processors
yeah they feel the whole bottom that
right they have the whole bottom full of
connectors oh great and ready I think
they are cold and then they are real
yeah yeah someone melted onto the
printed circuit board it's amazing that
all those points made good contacts
there so I do you know if I mean the
today's Pentiums are actually quite big
there are several centimeters in size I
guess the whole chip but the actual
calculation unit is it also as big or
other that you
your tips that you build on your wife's
are they smaller and the bigness of the
chip comes from the fact that you have
to put on all these macroscopic
connectors to the rest of the world
I think the size of the housing yeah
it's much more determining the as the
size of the the chip itself yeah yeah
yeah okay good so let's talk a little
bit about waivers scanners they well
again the purpose of them is to act as a
protector to project the mask onto the
wafer yeah we want we want to project a
pattern yeah under the mask the mask
itself is glass like it contains a
chromium bottom layer the chromium is
actually there the pattern that needs to
be projected on the chips although with
chips are very small the magnification
factor of the the lens we use is only
four times also the pattern on the
reticle the mask is rather small it's
very detailed and it is it it's the lens
making it smaller
yes it's making it smaller okay so let's
talk a little bit about the physical
dimensions of these machines because
people probably don't have a good image
of how these machines look they're
actually quite big right yeah if you
think on a regular beam or p.m. they are
quite smaller doing the same function
get a mask inside a projection optics
and they have a light source and yeah
well you put yeah edges on the wall and
we are thinking about the box of 30
centimeters maybe well when you look to
the wave scanner we want to demagnetize
due to a factor of four only and we are
talking about the box of five meters by
three meters by 2 meters so 3 meters
high and the floor space of 5 by 2
meters okay the Beast weighs about 15 to
20 tons and I guess they have to be
mounted on a special foundation so that
the truck that drives by the building
doesn't destroy all this stuff yeah they
are mounted indeed as on a so-called
pedestal in the cleanroom but even then
we have some additional measures taken
in order to isolate any vibrations from
the outside world into our systems yeah
well because yeah well you want to
illuminate a wafer which is about 300
millimeters and you want you want to
etch
a accuracy in the order of nanometers oh
well that is really something only the
slightest disturbance will end up in a
malfunctioning chip right so let's talk
a bit about the different components
that go into a way for a scanner by the
way why is it called scanner and not
wafer projector or something
the very first systems I wanted even
called wafer scanners but wait for step
us due to the nature how the image is
projected on the system because then the
the mask and the substrate wafer we put
at a complete standstill and then the
light went on and you had the new chip
so though it was a stepped process
that's what was a way for sniper yep
okay what we are doing now is that we
are making the image of one ship while
moving the mask and the substrate
synchronously to each other we really
scan the image of the the mask and
projected on the substrate why is that
is it for reason through put or the
biggest reason of it is that when you
make a wafer step up the image of the
chip has to fit into the diameter of the
lens image of the chip of the wafer no
one chip yes fit physically into the end
to the size of the lens yeah well if you
want to make bigger chips you have to
buy a bigger lens and a bigger lens is
very much more expensive so one way to
avoid buying a bigger lens is to use
only a strip of the lens the largest
strip that you can make over the land
but very small in your dimension and
then you can really draw your mask over
this slit as we call it and then you can
make a much larger image so in this case
you have the whole diameter of the lens
as the biggest dimension you can have
even if you imagine to fit a square into
a circular lens than obviously the site
sizes of the square are smaller than the
diameter yeah probably the root of
something yeah definitely that and that
is the reason that you want to do
scanning okay it also averages out
imperfection in the lens because you are
using more of the lens to illuminate
each individual spot that that's
probably getting a little bit too
complex yeah it's hard to picture
without seeing something here so okay so
let's go back to the to the different
components within a way for scanner I
guess from my perspective we should
probably start with the thing that holds
the way for Ryan well you could also
start at the the other end of the lights
the lights fine there is a relation
between the wavelength of the light
source and the dimension of the
structure that you can illuminate and it
tends to use light sources with a
decreasing wavelength so we start with
mercury lamps and we got into exile
lasers and for the next generation where
we use wavelength of 13 nanometers we
need to have some kind of a plasma
source in order to get the proper
wavelength out of it so you're using the
laser not because it can be focused that
well we're you know laser pointer or
cutting things where you put a lot of
energy in a small area I use the laser
because it is all the same wavelength
yeah it should we have a very constant
yeah wavelength and they're very
controllable wavelength but it all
should have some power because
unfortunately the the light has to
travel quite some distance and there's
also has to pass quite some glass so we
lose a lot of the energy and yeah well
the more energy we have at the wafer the
faster the illumination can take place
so light source itself is not part of
your machine right it has basically a
way where a glass tube you know comes in
where the light comes in right yeah
that's especially in that Christmas a
day there you have special laser
corridors but there's also due to a
safety measure because those lasers use
quite some some gases which are not too
healthy so they are when they're in the
production of the laser light the laser
light itself is not a problem yeah the
laser light has different properties
like intensity and wavelength and as we
call it it has a wavelength that is such
that you cannot see it there's an
intensity that
says once you saw it you won't see
anything again so yeah well you should
not look into the laser yeah okay
and I guess you can also if you have
several wafer scanners you know in a
production facility you can have only
one light source which makes this also
well that's not done any one light
source per wafer scanner higher okay
okay I would have thought that they
would centralize the light production
and then use it for several machines but
okay because the lens is the most
expensive part of our system you want to
utilize it as much so in any ideal
situation you would have 100%
utilization of the lens which means that
you would need a light source from 100%
of the time well you but you could split
the light but okay matter isn't done
finished so the light source is the
first ingredient kind of in there in the
in the workings of a wafer scanner so
that the light comes in to the big
machine into the wafer scanner and what
happens then well you're going to
condition this light so that the
homogeneity of this lie this is
optimized well such that each spot gets
the same amount of energy well and there
are other things being done in order to
optimize for for uniformity and also
polarization is taken into account and
there's a bunch of lenses and filters
yeah a lot of optics that that passes
will obviously be also some sensors
because we want to know the exact amount
of energy that is entering our system
and well then in the end we're going to
project the mask so we end up with a
what we call effector another word for
mask is reticle yeah right and we have a
subsystem called radical stage which is
the mechanical device holding and moving
the reticle over the lens through this
stream of light so that the light stream
is kind of fixed and then you're moving
through the light the reticle as well as
the wafer yeah we move it as we say
through the slit of light right and in
order to avoid that we illuminate pieces
of the reticle that we don't want to be
projected on the wafer we have some some
masking blades which determine the
actual part of the reticle that gets
illuminated because sometimes when you
are making very small
all ships multiple images might be put
on one reticle and then it is very
important that you illuminate the right
image on the reticle mm-hmm so this is
that you can switch which chip you
produce by just illuminating different
parts of the reticle instead of changing
it which is mechanically yeah expensive
well in fact not only that is expands we
also the reticle itself is a lot of
small structures need to be made on it
how are those built by the way I mean
it's this a manual process turn or is
there other special machines they're all
those special machines I think they are
with some kind of an e beam projection
they are etched on those red walls and
you might say why wouldn't you make
chips like that well the throughput of
such machines is too low to make a
profitable reproduction out of it in
case you speak you the listener speak or
listen or can understand German we've
had an episode about nano structures and
surface modification not too long ago
and I guess some of these techniques are
used to build the reticle I can imagine
yeah so the light passes through the
reticle and it's this where the big
expensive Carl Zeiss lenses have already
been used or are they used after that
when you focus the light onto the well
the the the biggest amount of money
comes then off in radical has been
passed then we go through a lens and
yeah well you might think that just yeah
magnifying by a factor of 0.25 or d
magnifying by a factor of four well
that's not a big deal but we are talking
about the lens that has a height of 1
meter and a diameter of 60 or 70
centimeters stack of lenses yeah that's
one land this is a lot of optics yeah
because also in that place you want to
manipulate some of the lens elements in
certain directions
- yeah well you want to have the best
image out of it so let's let's step back
that the reason why the lenses are so
important and that's so expensive is
because the projection has to be of an
extremely good quality you don't want
any aberrations in it right
definitely yeah so any aberration will
affect the position and the focus of the
image that you are going to project
if you only make small deviations out of
it those contact points of your
transistors won't compact anymore yeah
yeah so it'd mean probably means that if
these lenses are 60 70 centimeters in
diameter you only use a part of it for
the actual light that's interesting the
rest is just to make the lens good yeah
definitely yeah okay okay so the light
goes down through the lens and then it's
a substrate but the substrate doesn't
float by magic in the system so we are a
subsystem that's called wave for stage
which is holding this silicon disk is
wafer yeah it also has to move it
because here what we talked about before
radical and wave form moved
synchronously with each other in order
to make the image how fast are they
moved one meter per second radical stage
well the magnification effect of four so
25 centimeters per second on waiting for
stage level okay and well I guess that's
that's it that's it so we are talking
about moving kilograms of mass and then
yeah well being able to control their
position at nanometer scale yeah so
let's talk a little bit about some of
these challenges and how you solve them
when I was first in the ASML building
they were in the in the reception area
there is a very old machine from I guess
from the 80s may be bidding here
beginning of the 90s when the movement
of some of these things was hydraulic
yeah I can't imagine that that's how you
do it today so let's talk a little bit
about how you make it so that you can do
these high precision movements and high
precision projections
did you know right the system that you
are referring to is I had I'd Rolex I
think at that time it could obtain the
required accuracy but it must be it must
have been a problem with contamination
of all this hydraulic fluid flying
around yeah well you maybe might not see
it but on nanometer scale definitely
some particles must be coming out of it
yeah so that's not the way we are doing
it now we use linear motors Magnus ear
bearings and all those kind of stuff so
I have some mechanics moving mm-hmm I
also understand that there is between
the lens where the light comes out and
the wave
you have water of these days yep and the
fact that's a technique that's also
already very old because when they used
to make microscopes in Middle Ages
underneath only Avenue they already
discovered that when you put a drop of
oil between the object you would want to
see in the lens that the image quality
enhanced enormous Lee why is that well
this due to the diffraction their
properties of light from glass to air
it's different when you're going from
glass to water and it has some positive
effects on your depth of focus which
makes your system more robust more
tolerant against any deviations into
your focus behavior but on the other
hand you have to make sure that there
aren't any air bubbles in the water and
you as you move your lens or well don't
move the lens you move the wafer but
still there is something moving between
well yeah you know it's that's also
challenging well let the the wafer is
not flat in the end and so we have a lot
of steaks on top of it so it's quite
irregular surface so indeed you must be
sure that no air bubbles are getting in
because well they are magnification
glass on their own yeah and they will
destroy the image in a way that you
don't have a work in ship anymore
and that's not the only thing as a
challenge but also being sure that no
particles are loosened from the wafer
and floating around into this water bath
it's one of the challenges the
photoresist should not dissolve into
this water and definitely you don't want
to flood your system with water so you
have to be careful to make sure that the
the water is only in the area below the
lens and yeah well that is that requires
quite some engineering are you allowed
to talk about what you do or is that
secret I can say that this sub system
that is made for that is called
immersion hood and several revisions of
that immersion would have been developed
we had to develop it fast and they will
have some they have certain regressions
several versions of this emergent have
been made and still some some research
is going on on that area in order to
develop the best immersion that we can
come up with is that more
experimentation or is there any
mathematics physics / other science
stuff you can actually calculate
you know or is that really just trying
it out and I smell it was really a
matter of research and experimentation
okay it was a technique and we didn't
apply in the past and we only were using
optics mechanics but not that much fluid
dynamics until that moment yeah and it
turned out as within a lot of areas that
when you are going to work on it on a
nanometer scale there's not much prior
experience with it on other fields so
you know what we have to discover a lot
of things ourselves
yeah so you talked about the movement
and the positioning which is obviously
critical I know from my own playing
around as a child with electronics that
there are two ways how you can position
something either with a stepper motor
and you count the steps basically and
you know where you are or you have a
quote normal motor but then you need
something that measures the position and
and and controls as a control loop
controls the position you're doing the
letter and we are doing the letter e you
have very good server engineers who
develop this this control loop and we
use quite some some electronics in order
to be able to process it control loops
are characterized with a silver
frequency and things like jitter and
what we call IO delay properties which
which determine how well we are capable
of following the setpoint
as it is called it's always a pleasure
the servo engineers always want a faster
control loop and they also want to put
more stuff in it and say well we have
the software department we also have to
fiddle with being able to do it in time
it's real-time and better program right
at top scale eyes I think we'll get back
to that in a second but how do you
actually measure the position do you do
that with I guess maybe another bunch of
lasers that maybe we use interferometer
base their positioning in systems I mean
these grants have used a a similar
system but then the laser beam is
reduced in length so we position them on
a different space and that by that we
can
even increase the accuracy of our system
okay okay so let's let's talk a little
bit about the software I guess as you
say there is basically a embedded
control real-time system going on I
wanna talk a little bit about that there
is a lot of software into the system and
only only the lowest layers of this
embedded part although I know most of
that part because I since the time I've
been here I've been working at the
embedded software but I know there are I
think now 25 or 30 million lines of code
in our system mostly C code a little bit
of a yeah a little bit of Python it's a
layered architecture and it goes from
well interacting with the fab automation
system the graphical user interface all
the calibration software a metrology
software and then going down to the
embedded part where all the subsystems
are located just as a comment metrology
is not as sloppy pronunciation of
Meteorology which is the weather stuff
metrology is the science of measuring
measuring right exactly yeah just to be
be sure although with a allows some
meteorology like aspects in our systems
like air pressure and because that
determines the accuracy on which you can
imagine the position because well the
air where the laser of the
interferometer is passing through
determines the quality of the received
signal you can imagine that driving on
the highway and the summers day you see
this is a UH vibrating those kind of
effects you want to prevent or avoid
when you're measuring position there's
also kind of again shows or illustrates
how precise all of this stuff oh yeah
definitely that's that's the reason why
those areas where those beams of going
through a very well well conditioned
you're working on a new class / family
of machines they're called EUV right so
how they're how they're different from
the last one what's the innovation this
time yeah well UV is an abbreviation for
extreme UV and tract we already
mentioned it briefly in the
previous part when we talked about the
wavelength the current systems work with
a laser which emits a light source with
the wavelength of 193 nanometer and in
order to be able to project small
structures we have to cut down the
wavelength through 13 nanometers which
brings in you the area of extreme UV and
well we cannot use a regular excite
Malaysia for that use a different light
source which emits just is right
wavelength however there is some problem
with that kind of light and that is that
it's completely absorbed by most
substances even air so in order to have
some of that light on the wafer we have
to make the big part of our system in
complete vacuum vacuum again there's a
technique which we did not handle in the
previous systems this is actually really
interesting again when I when I saw this
hydraulics thing first you have been
building the same kinds of machines for
years now for decades maybe even but the
challenges the techniques you use the
engineering the sciences that are
involved they change whole time yeah we
have to deal with vacuum engineering we
should probably didn't do before exactly
yes and it's always good when you look
to that developments that you realize
again that the system in principle is
the same as this Bheema there is source
of light yeah in projection system the
mask and the substrate yeah so when you
compare to software the interface is
more or less the same but we are talking
about a different implementation yeah
yeah so I think people have heard about
Moore's law which basically means that
everything gets twice as fast or twice
as small or twice as big in terms of
memory every 18 to 24 months does this
mean that you have to change the
machines every 18 to 24 months is every
more cycle does it mean a different way
of producing the chips or is that no
it's not because then in that case you
would I think have 30 of generations of
systems well we definitely did not make
30 okay
until you introduce a new approach when
I started in 1998 we introduced the twin
scan
systems before that we had pass system
so there was a new generation and I
think now our AV system is again a new
generation so from 1998 to 2010 is 12
years so let's say every 10 years we
really make a real new platform
obviously there are many machine-type
derived from such a platform bit sure
but they don't they they are not
different in terms of the principle how
they work but rather in terms of size
throughput maybe the speed is well and
we put in a new upgraded version of the
projection optics right I are okay and
that that changes a little bit now and
that is also one of the drivers for
being able to make smaller chips okay
this sounds like a really a challenging
environment to work with because maybe
not as a person but at least as a
company you have to you have to you know
you have to hire vacuum vacuum engineers
or whatever you call these guys I don't
know what this is yeah science is this
yeah that's definitely true it well what
I like about this company I like it
because obviously otherwise I wouldn't
have been here for four twelve years is
that the principles can be explained and
yeah well regular school every engineer
here at age male has a more or less
basic understanding of the system
however when you really go to work at a
subsystem then you get to learn about a
lot of details you never would have
thought of and that is what I think
makes it interesting to work here and we
are well it's it's it's a highly dynamic
organization we are working in a very
cyclic industry so it gets from booming
down to really really bad times and well
I smell is is really focused on being
able to survive and do the downturns as
we call them and really to succeed and
to explode into those terms and in fact
we are in one of those terms right now
okay and well it's even that booming
that they are asking guys from
development to help out in production in
order to make sure that we can produce
sufficient systems and well and as it is
now obviously we are also
a lot of people from various disciplines
you know software mechanics if you
really know your job and you really want
to work in the way exciting environment
well this is one okay so I guess people
can contact your company through the
website advertisement part of the show I
guess we put a link directly to the
recruiting email address on the website
yeah that would be nice yeah no problem
okay so did we forget anything important
all right did we kind of cover it at
that kind of level of detail I think we
recovered it more or less yeah your
heart is into technology I wouldn't know
what any better spot to beat and then
over here it's very interdisciplinary
interdisciplinary oh yeah yeah yeah okay
then well thank you very much for being
on the show thank you much for getting
the opportunity to be here
sure thanks so that's it I hope it was
interesting although it was a bit
off-topic well I guess you could let us
know whether you've liked it or not and
want to hear more stuff like that in the
future we also thank Wilbert Albertson
ASML for taking part in the discussion
and well thank you for listening
talk to you next time bye
thanks for listening to software
engineering radio as a radio is an
educational program brought to you by
hillside Europe if you want more
information about the podcast and the
other episodes visit our website at se -
radio dotnet if you want to support us
you can donate to the SA radio team by
at the website or you can advertise for
se radio for example by clicking on the
Digg reddit delicious and slashed up
buttons or by talking about us on
Twitter and Facebook
you can also support us by joining team
and shouldering some of the work to
contact the team please send email to
team at se - radio net or if your
feedback is specific to an episode
please use the comments facility on the
website so other people can react to
your comments this episode of SU radio
as well as all other episodes are
licensed under a creative commons 2.5
license please see the website for
details
[Music]